all right welcome everyone
it's 7 11 23 we're in cohort three in
our first discussion of chapter eight so
we'll head over to
chapter eight
and look at some questions and comments
but first
does anyone wanna
bring up any
uh just general or thoughts or
Reflections on chapter eight
um Ollie
uh well yes
um actually chapter 8 is obviously the
title suggests uh is a kind of
complementary to uh chapter seven uh in
terms of uh being the continuous time
counterpart to uh the active inference
formulation of discrete time uh so uh as
we saw previously in chapter four uh we
have both continuous time version and
discrete time version of active
inference employing different
mathematical Technologies and techniques
but of course they can be regarded as a
kind of
uh formulating the uh the same or at
least a similar formulation just using
uh different mathematical techniques so
namely in a discrete time case uh we use
uh matrices to represent uh States
Transitions and so on
um but in a continuous time we use
generalized coordinates
in order to describe the states and not
just I mean discrete matrices for States
and also
the starting point of formalizing active
inference in continuous time also
differs a bit because
uh in continuous time version we begin
with a version or a variant of Idol's
stochastic equation
by representing a flow plus random
variable and then trying to somehow uh
formulate the flows in terms of
increasingly
granular way and
yeah tracing the trajectory through the
uh State space continuous time State
space uh employing that
um I mean Taylor expansions and other
mathematical Technologies and so on
great all of you
uh yeah what do you mean by granular
here
so I mean uh it was a stochastic
equation is a very general equation
describing any kind of sorry
differential stochastic uh phenomenon
but in this case we focus on a
particular kinds of State space with
particular kinds of behaviors so
especially in active inference we focus
on active agents as opposed to a more
General sense of the term uh such as I
mean
describing the whole behavior of a
self-organizing system or even a simple
simple system that can be basically
described with a simple statistical
physics so the focus of active inference
as I said is uh the the agents that
doesn't that that don't have empty set
of active States right but of course it
can also be generalized to other kinds
of Agents with empty active States uh
but but the active inference framework
or fep don't have anything particularly
interesting to say about those other
kinds of Agents uh that's what I meant
of granular we focus on a subset of the
systems that can be described through it
was a stochastic equation
okay
cool thank you we cannot come back to
some of these uh and also Ali we will be
keeping in mind that we need to make the
videos for
seven eight nine
four five
sure yeah whatever whatever you want
um
um okay anyone else want to just have
any general thought or question raising
their hand or or in the chat on on a on
and continuous time
I really like that chapters two and
three give us
the kind of uh two ways to get there to
active the low road and the high road
the how and the why
and now it's like we're in the city
and now there's two restaurants or
there's like two doors to the restaurant
with the discrete and the continuous
time so it's another dyad of chapters
with seven and eight
and another juxtaposition that gives us
Parallax and helps us like understand
more about each of these two methods
by um highlighting
on one hand situations where they seem
to apply
uh more naturally
for example the discrete time
formulation seems to be a natural fit
for discrete decision making tasks like
Which slot machine are you going to pull
whereas The Continuous time
model
seems to be a more natural fit for
analog perception control systems like
proprioception and uh sensory motor
Behavior
and chapter 8 is also going to get us to
hybrid nested models
for example a model with two layers
where the lower levels continuous time
and the higher level is discrete time so
that kind of represents like a just a
decision-making central nervous system
that's dispatching
um commands to a continuous time sensory
motor body
and that is also explored in the sort of
um folk psychological active inference
work where you can kind of get the the
um
synthesis of continuous and discrete
time models
anyone else wanna
add a comment on eight before we start
to look through it
yeah I have a question
um
maybe it's nice to verify as my video on
let's see
um I was wondering if there are any good
resources on applications of continuous
active inference because
um up until now I've
worked on two projects with active
interns but only working with discrete
States state space models and I was
wondering if there is any like good
papers on continuous active inference
and it's it's sort of
um representative applications
at the endicipation
yeah I think this table has some oh yeah
yeah I'm so sorry for asking a redundant
question no no it's it's it's all good
these are not all the applications but
let's just look at the topics that they
have raised so the bird song is
definitely a classic
um
single singing bird and uh to singing
birds
ocular motor Behavior
reflex Behavior more eye Behavior
um different
cognitive States
more eye Behavior
this is one of the few papers on mirror
neurons
okay
um attention
I believe this is attention being
modeled in a slightly different approach
um this is a continuous time attentional
framework whereas there the um sanfed
Smith paper uses
um discrete time attention
the hybrid and self-organizing but I
um
there's other
um citations and and I'm sure you could
come up with many more things
and also like one of the kind of model
annotation tasks that I think would be
super helpful in terms of meta-analysis
would be like for each paper
um
how could you how can we describe how
can we describe the active inference
models they used
so then we could just like filter a
table where are the discrete time models
where are the continuous time models
where are the nested models where are
the models that use
yeah
yeah yeah
thank you for the overview cool
okay
so um
from the figures
figure 4.3
recall that
the discrete time and the continuous
time generative models
have some structural similarities
at the same time they have important
differences
and also partially this is uh signaled
with a difference in notation
so like hidden states are going to be
reflected with x in continuous time not
s
observables are reflected with Y not o
uh
causal interventions and the system are
reflected in V not pi
and really the most important difference
is that whereas in the discrete time you
have past present and future
explicit State predictions
in the continuous time setting
you're using the generalized coordinates
of motion
where X is the hidden State at a given
time
and X Prime is the derivative of the
Hidden State how it's changing Through
Time so the B Matrix which is the
transition Matrix in discrete time
describing how States go from one time
step to another how the hidden States
change here is describing like kind of
like the derivative or the integration
function because it's describing how
derivatives are linked to each other
and what causes do in the model is the
influence how derivatives change Through
Time
here's the
um
Edo calculus type
equations that Ali spoke to First
we have
observable states are a function G of
hidden States that's the flow and some
stochastic noise term about y sensor
noise
and then x dot
rate of change in x
is a function of the Hidden State at the
current time and the causal forces on
the system at that time plus a
fluctuation term on x
action is absent in equation 8.1
this is because action is part of the
generative process not the generative
model
foreign
are definitions of generative process
and generative model
the generative model only deals with
those variables directly influenced by
States external to a Markov blanket
what do you think about this Ali
uh well yeah actually
um
this is one of the points that that was
kind of brought up in
in the discussion with Maxwell because
as we know generative model I mean if we
consider fep as this a kind of General
framework or theoretical framework to
describe the behavior of the things
quote-unquote things that persist
through time we can theoretically
describe
uh the generative model as containing
any kinds of different situations both
containing active States and uh or in
other words with active States and also
with empty set of active States uh so
but as I said before I believe active
inference is more concerned with the
situations that have non-empty set of
activist States in other words they have
the ability to perform or to undertake
um
or to put to put it in a more uh
rigorous terms to kind of engage in a
causal intervention with the environment
both
in terms of updating the generator model
and also uh if effectuating some
some changes in the environment that can
fit better with their generative models
so yeah that's I mean what's meant here
by directly influenced by States
external to a mark of blanket means the
states
from the environment that can
dynamically act upon the markup blanket
in order to make it more suitable or
more adapted to the environment
through the generation of the markup
blankets I'm sorry degenerative model
and also minimizing the free energy
yeah thank you it it looks like the
difference here between 8.1 and 8.2
other than the Bolding of the equations
is like V
a static
variable
is replaced by a controllable
action
parameter
so now a specific
implementation of
equations 8.1 8.2 are going to be
described
so now that uh Ali go for it
uh sorry I forgot to mention something
uh there was a debate on Twitter a
couple of days ago about whether or not
fpp can be applied to inert objects such
as rocks which is a uh I mean uh one of
the debates that's been going on for a
long time now but uh you see
theoretically it can be applied to any
kinds of object even to a manure to rock
but the only difference here is that
inner truck
has an empty set of Acts of the states
that's it so if we take a non-empty set
of active states such as I don't know
biological organisms or sentience agents
and so on
um that would
also employ the same kind of
mathematical Technologies but the only
difference would be the existence of
non-empty set of active States
sure I I would almost also say though
that
it's not that the active states are
empty for an inert or a classical or a
conservative object
that they're just
um
trivial
for example just outputting a stationary
action state
um
okay so now they're going to give a
specific
um example of what this pair of
equations looks like
and there's a point attractor
so this is going to be kind of moving us
towards a um uh
uh continuous time system where there's
a fixed attracting point where if the um
the actuators below the fixed point it's
going to go up and if it's above the
fixed point it's going to go down and so
this is going to be the kind of model
that's used for isocades and for like
elbow movements and things like that
generative process is specified
the hidden state is basically just
passed through and the action is
basically just passed through
V is in the generative model
V
U is in the generative process
this connects to the equilibrium points
hypothesis
again it relates to a proprioceptive
prediction
about expected
proprioceptive feedback coming from for
example the limbs or the eyes
this enables action to be
prediction fulfillment
rather than for example reward
maximization or utility maximization
directly
this relates to an extensive discussion
on forwards and inverse modeling
and interactionism and instructionism
and some of that was explored in the
skillful performance
live stream
now they're going to move from this
fixed Point attractor
into
a spring attractor
so now there's going to be an
oscillatory uh
attraction with dampening
and that is going to require not just a
um
uh scalar description
of the attractive points
but we're going to start moving into
this generalized coordinate way of
thinking where we're going to be
tracking kind of a vector
of position and velocity and generalized
coordinates you can think of they keep
going like you could have put position
velocity acceleration and so on
so they kind of just work through that
and say yeah you could also just write
down the generative model where not just
the the elbow wants to be at 90 degrees
and it's at 80 so it extends out to 90
but now you could have one where it goes
and it overshoots 90 and then dampens it
back to 90. and you could continue to
develop these um uh generalized
coordinate based systems or you could
think about the fixed points being
attractors in a generalized coordinate
space
this discussion connects us to
consideration of dynamical systems more
broadly fixed point tractor the spring
attractor those were both dynamical
systems and so now we're kind of fully
in this dynamical systems setting
which is natural for continuous time
um discussions and
um stochastic differential equations and
all of this some topics that are
certainly relevant for the discrete time
setting but are more naturally addressed
in continuous time
so in chapter five we looked at this
spinal cord cross section
and it was discussed as a simple uh
proprioceptive input
descending fixed Point prediction
and then the residual was being passed
on the error signal was being passed
forward to engage bodily movements so
like if the proprioceptive data and the
descending prediction were identical
there's no discrepancy no motion occurs
whereas when there is a discrepancy
between the expectation
of proprioception and the incoming
proprioception this triggers
um a discrepancy and and
um that discrepancy is resolved through
movement
so now that example from chapter five
is being re-approached
using the formalisms and the continuous
time setting that we see in chapter
eight
here we have a box
on Precision attention and sensory
attenuation
um this is going to cover
several
different topics
um
first precision and attention
are described as synonymous
um
the that's a pretty General claim
however
um one can think of as something that's
being attended to highly
is giving precise inputs and therefore
is Salient it's relevant it updates the
model a lot if something is not being
attended to in the limit that is
equivalent to something that has zero
Precision it's infinitely ambiguous and
therefore it doesn't update the model
because it's not Salient it's not
relevant
so it's kind of a general point about
precision and attention
and one way that this plays out
in relationship to
um motor control
and some extremely interesting and
unique explanations and predictions
arising
about Precision attention and motor
control
in a predictive processing setting
is this topic of sensory attenuation in
motor generation
so attenuation means diminishment and in
some ways attenuation even though it
sounds like basically the same word is
like the opposite of attention it just
means it's like dis attention or like uh
alleviation of attention
um does anyone want to like give a
thought or explanation about what is the
role of of sensory attenuation in motor
initiation and fulfillment
okay let's give a thought on it
um
so
if one is sitting down in a chair
the accurate belief to have is that I is
I am sitting down
how without invoking goals
or explicit predictions about future
time points
how do we
go from
having an accurate belief I am sitting
down to having an accurate belief that I
am standing up I mean the transition
between those two steps basically two
things have to happen you have to change
your mind
thinking you're sitting down to thinking
that you're standing up and you have to
change the world you actually have to go
from sitting down to standing up that's
action
and so how does that happen well the
issue is that if you're sitting down and
you have a high Precision accurate
belief I am sitting down
and then you change or you try to change
your expectation or your preference or
your fixed point or your set point
standing up
it's going to be like no that's unlikely
all of our proprioceptive evidence is
telling us that we're sitting down
and so
um in in that way like the body would
kind of be like an anchor and it would
pull the cognitive belief back to no
actually we're sitting down
so if you just try to be like we're
sitting down and we know that we're
sitting down and you just try to say
okay now we're standing up but the
body's still sitting down if you have
high attention on the proprioceptive
inputs then that cognitive belief gets
dragged back and so you end up not
initiating motor movements
and so the resolution of this challenge
is you update your belief I am standing
up
while you're sitting down
meanwhile you engage in sensory
attenuation
you release the attention on the
proprioceptive input
and during that alleviation of attention
to proprioceptive input
you can think about the the Distribution
on proprioceptive inputs to actually
include standing up
so now that is a more viable hypothesis
the posterior probability becomes higher
then action selection can be engaged to
fulfill that expectation about standing
up and so voila now you're standing up
and you think you're standing up and
then you can re-engage Precision so that
now you can have that precise belief
that you're standing up whereas
previously you had a precise belief that
you were sitting down
and the key step was kind of like you're
driving on the road
it's like attention is like the gas
you pull off the gas make the turn and
then re-engage the gas and another
example of this is in our isocades when
our gaze is fixed we have high Precision
on our visual input
when we do an isocate transiently IT
suppresses visual precision
and that's why during cicades which
happens several times a second
we don't see like a big blur
because it's almost like a blink now
it's not your eyelids coming over your
eyes but it's actually an attentional
blink when you do a cicade
which is why the um
highly
um
Dynamic input during a cicade is
suppressed or not attended to
so that we end up having the generative
experience of fixed high percentage
precision Vision and then we blink into
another fixed High Precision visual
input with a suppression of attention
during the cicade
and different pathologies can be
understood as challenges associated with
initiating movements
or with terminating movement or with
continuing movements
and so different different
um pathologies have been associated with
this so certain motor dyskinesias where
somebody may have a challenge initiating
a movement but once they are moving like
they walk normally
or on the other hand there are
um different motor pathologies
any thoughts or comments on this this is
kind of an interesting topic
even just outside of this embodied or or
technical setting just like this idea
that
in order for
the possible to be actualized
there has to be a a
relaxation on the actual
to enable the movements to to a
different space
and here's the cyclical precision
[Music]
and this has been Associated
um
heavily with differences in the
neurophysiology of vision
okay
again just raise your hand or write
anything in the uh
chat if you want
a classic dynamical systems model from
ecology is going to be introduced and
this is the laka Volterra Dynamics
sometimes it's called Predator prey
Dynamics
or especially in the context of
um neural Darwinism
and dynamical systems in neuroscience
sometimes this is called winnerless
competition
because as you can see here
in the psychological example like it's
not that the herbivores are trying to
defeat the plants in fact they have a
relationship where if the herbivores are
transiently succeeding in decreasing the
plant numbers then they will have this
like demographic collapse and so this is
the winnerless competition is you have
dynamical oscillations and so this
describes ecological Dynamics but also
it describes activity
um patterns amongst brain regions like
two systems
that have an oscillatory repressive
consequence on each other a
repressolator
that will have this kind of winnerless
competition dynamic
so
um this is just a classic dynamical
system
and in the SPM textbook the lock of
ultera is used to describe these winner
lists competitions neural darwinist
Dynamics
um
these three traces plant herbivore and
carnivore you can think of them as like
in this graph like a plot happening
through time
or you could imagine a cube with like
the X the Y and the Z axis being plant
herbivore carnivore Dynamics and so this
system can be represented as three
traces along the x-axis here or you can
imagine it as like a movement in a
three-dimensional Cube
and so if we're spending a lot of time
up in this corner you can think about
what that would mean and so on and then
on that Cube
just like the girdle Escher Bach book
cover
you can project
from the three-dimensional Cube down to
a two Dimension and that would be like
putting a camera on one side of the cube
and just taking a picture
so here we're looking at the herbivore
by plant
um projection of the cube and it has
this kind of oscillatory cycle
here it's approximately periodic because
there's this dampening but you could
design a system that has different
behaviors
now the lock of Volterra
is going to be applied
in a few different active inference
contexts
the first
is in the eye blink
conditioning
and so this is um conditioned stimulus
and unconditioned stimulus
so this is kind of like a classical
scenarian
behaviorist paradigm
of um
of
um Behavior action
blinking
associated with conditioned and
unconditioned stimuli
using this dynamical systems framework
whereas in the discrete time we'd have
okay time step one do we get this
stimulus or that stimulus or neither and
then what do we do and how do we make
the decision and then the next time step
this happens all of that is happening in
this kind of continuous unfolding
winnerless competition setting
so that's the first example
um on the left side that's the blink the
unconditioned stimulus
um produces a a blink that's alert
Association
and the right example
which um also listened to Thomas parr's
bookstream 2.1 when he gives a little
more of the history
um or
we we um
we we have a few in the Thomas part 227
page
he he he gave some great
history here
talking about how the generalized
filtering and continuous State space
approach was early on being the most
developed people started wanting to get
sequential Dynamics
so they developed the kind of model that
we're going to see right here like here
this is like sequential writing Dynamics
clearly there's a repetitive Motif
that's being repeated
sequentially
but then the desire to explicitly
sequentially encode beliefs and to
engage in explicit planning as inference
motivated the work in discrete
state-space models where planning as
inference is a more natural fit
of course by the end of the chapter
we're going to be kind of merging these
two different kinds of models together
but here's an example of lockabletera
dynamical systems Dynamics
in handwriting setting
so it's kind of like a sequence of
points that are being targeted and
driven through
sequentially
by hand
short box 8.2 on learning in continuous
models
slightly technical note
perhaps um sanjeev's textbook will
clarify some of these pieces
[Music]
um
however using LaPlace approximation so a
quadratic approximator
were able to
um use integrals on continuous
distributions to specify the
attention-weighted evidence grade
gradients
but this is just kind of little
encapsulated box
Ali
I just wanted to mention a small typo in
box 8.2 so the third line in the second
block of equations should be minus
d s mu Theta so yeah the minus in front
of
D I suppose is
should be added
thank you good dog let me have this one
thank you
all right now we're going to move into a
second class so just like it the first
we saw like the simple Point attractor
and then the hooke's law the tractor
spring
now in this dynamical setting we're
going to have kind of two
levels of sophistication of dynamical
systems models the first one was the
generalized lockabletera system the
second one is the Lorenz system a
lorenza tractor which is a canonical
example of a of a complex sort of a
chaotic system and it's a super
fascinating story with Lorenz and his
work in weather prediction and that was
of course one of the most important
moments of the complexity and the
computational chaos research of the last
hundred years
this is also explored a lot more in live
stream 34 on
um uh Markov blankets and and stochastic
chaos I believe
where
um solitary and coupled lorenza tractors
are modeled
um it's a super fascinating work
um generalized synchrony is going to be
unpacked in the setting of Birdsong
which was a friston frith paper may have
one slightly earlier than this but the
2015 is kind of the classic citation
and this is seen as
a kind of Exemplar of multi-agent
inference problems when they are quote
singing from the same hymn sheet as Carl
always says
and so the bird song attractor is going
to leverage the lorenza tractor
described above
and there's going to be two
Lorenz attractors coupled through
communication reflecting bird song
and some details of those attractors are
going to be
um described and simulated
and the kind of
um big takeaway here
is that the generalized synchrony is
accomplished through communication
so here we have the first and the second
bird on the X and on the y-axis
we can think about this
line Y equals X line as being a manifold
that would reflect perfect synchrony so
if you could describe movement on this
two-dimensional
plane
by appealing only to a movement along a
single line you would have reduced a
two-dimensional setting into a
one-dimensional setting and that's like
a dimensional reduction and that's
called a statistical manifold
before learning
while there is overall
adherence towards this Y equals X line
we see that after learning
the
manifold um the behaviors tightened
immensely around the manifold that
represents
um the the learning to synchronize
between these two birds
the two birds joint trajectories can
find to an almost one-dimensional
Subspace indicating synchronization
also it's kind of a cool nod to fractal
dimensions
like if it was perfectly on this line
you'd only need one dimension
if it was purely
covering the whole 2D space you would
need two Dimensions so then you can
think about this as being slightly
higher than one dimensional
this connects
back to the earlier attention and
attenuation
and this alternation of listening and
singing it's kind of like now this is
not all communicative settings and
there's more work on Communications but
it's kind of a fun Paradigm we're
basically like the bird expects there to
be singing both Birds expect there to be
singing it's like you know
insert your favorite cultural singing
moment
um
if you're gonna sing
my preferences will be fulfilled through
perception
and if I'm missing my preferences are
going to be filled through action
fulfilling my preferences through action
is going to reduce my sensory attention
to perception until eventually it's like
whoa I'm not sure what's happening I'm
going to stop singing
and then in that silence the other birds
gonna go oh my preferences were being
fulfilled by listening attentively
I'm not hearing it anymore I better
reduce this discrepancy by taking action
because listening harder isn't going to
help
because that's not going to make the
song happen and so that's singing from
the same hymn sheet like Carl says
um and it relates to
um
joint uh you know shared shared regimes
of expectation and Joint perception
action and multi-agent systems
and the generalized synchrony doesn't
mean lockstep generalized synchrony
doesn't mean both birds are seeing
identically and then they're both
silence
generalized synchrony means that there's
Mutual information
between these two coupled systems
such that there is an information
geometric manifold that represents their
joint movement
but it doesn't have to be a lock step
same behavior at the same time turn
taking is also an example of generalized
synchrony
8.5 gets to hybrid discrete and
continuous models so here we see a
nested model there's a line that's
supposed to be between pi and G
obviously and in the top level we see
the discrete time generative model
T minus 1 t and t plus one we see all
the letters that we know and love from
um chapter seven a b d
but then within each time step of the
higher order model we see the continuous
time model with the generalized
coordinates of motion
and so this was unpacked in live stream
46 octave inference does not contradict
folk psychology
where the top level was called decision
active inference or Dai
and the bottom was called motor active
inference or m-a-i because somebody can
think about
the discrete the discrete decision
making on the top can be like am I going
to raise my left hand or raise my right
hand
and that's a discreet decision there's
no need to um make it an uh um analog
but then with the descending
command that it's going to be okay raise
my right hand
then we can engage that whole motor
fixed point
apparatus of the continuous time model
whether we do it with a lockable Terra
or a um or lorenza tractor or the
hooke's law or just a simple Point
attractor so all the kind of continuous
time tools that we saw earlier in the
chapter
we can deploy in the setting
of a nested model with a discrete time
decision maker on top and a continuous
time on the bottom which may articulate
better with the seemingly analog nature
of perception and action
in the last mile
this is a little bit of Machinery that
helps map between
the uh discrete selection of Target
locations
into the continuous setting where those
targets locations can be
released
and an example of this is using
um an isocate
where there's a discrete movement of a
Target location followed by a continuous
time trajectory of the eye cicating to
that
box 8.3 again raises just some sort of
super Curt um analysis of a
sophisticated topic which is a gaussian
mixture model
and like we know the gaussian we love
the calcium we know we contractibly
optimize it and so on and so on it does
an incredible job of approximating
distributions that have a Central Mass
tendency
a lot of statistical tools work
incredibly for gaussian but of course
not all gaussians are going to describe
given complex distributions but the good
news whether you approaches from a
gaussian mixture model or a hierarchical
gaussian filter or just generalized
filtering is that it turns out that
through composition of gaussians
you can build complex distributions
that have almost arbitrary
characteristics so that's kind of a way
to get like the attractability
of gaussians
but also for example make a bimodal
distribution or trimodal distribution
this engages the challenge of Bayesian
model reduction Bayesian model selection
structure learning
table 8.1 closes with some discussion of
continuous time model advances
and that ends the relatively short
but pretty dense chapter eight
does anyone yeah Olivia
yeah uh yeah I have a question I'm not
sure I can formulate it uh well but
um the thing is you know when we think
in terms of discrete time model uh we
usually we know we think in terms of
regular time steps
uh and with this mixed you know uh
continuous and discrete time model uh
you know it's not possible to to model a
behavior in continuous time and you know
uh to have
um the discrete time step to arrive at
different uh I would say you know
different diets after different duration
within the continuous time model you
know when you reach uh you know a
Criterion in the continuous time model
you get to a Next Step at the top level
um
okay just one thought on that are you
referring to a model where the discrete
time steps are are actually in
homogeneous
or yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah so no no no
no no no regular in time so for example
you will imagine you know a search task
uh happening in uh you know in
continuous time uh and you reach you
know a crit Ion at some point uh and
depending on the on the steps you know
you can reach that uh earlier or later
but when you reach a secretary and you
jump you know at the top level uh so you
make your decision and you jump at the
top level
yes so
one interesting question is how could
that logic be encoded into the
generative model
another way to view that setting would
be you'd have a generative model
um that does have like a real
um Regular
um chronology
but then you're modeling samples
potentially like poisson distributed
samples
from a regular continuous or discrete
timeline
so the delta T of the samples is not
necessarily homogeneous
but the underlying substrate of the
model would be
so observations are not coming in
regularly actions are potentially not
being taken regularly
but there is a clock that has regularity
that would be the sort of sampling based
approach to dealing with this um time
heterogeneity
than the other approach would be somehow
to figure out through
um a composition of discrete and or
continuous models
um can you encode
um a temporal logic
when this condition is met then this
happens yeah yeah yeah
it's an interesting area and I mean this
this uh
folks psychological
or just nested hybrid model
I mean this is just a hint
and so it would be really awesome I
think to see the the Matlab or the other
code implementations so we could do okay
now let's do this is a two by two Matrix
and this one is that um spring attractor
okay now this is a three by three Matrix
and this one's the lock of Volterra I
think that if we could um
unroll those systems a little bit
um
more clearly
I I think we'd have some really
um illustrative Dynamics
okay awesome well next week we will um
return for a second discussion on
chapter eight we'll just go straight to
the questions and um
Ali I think we'll be ready to do our
chapter eight review when the time is
right
sure yeah
all right
thank you all
uh see you next time
thank you